Welcome back. In this lesson we'll be exploring two powerful tools in TypeScript, Inums, and
the literal types. So these help you define strict sets of values. Like, for example, user roles,
directions, or maybe status codes, and this makes your code more expressive, predictable,
and of course self documenting. So let's first of all talk about Inums.
So what exactly are Inums? Well, an Inum is short for enumeration. So a way to define a name
set of constants, so instead of using a magic string, so numbers, we give each value a meaningful name.
So let's do Inum, and let's say, for example, we're doing roles. So role like this, and we then
simply define the list of roles that we want to obtain it. So it may be an admin, user,
editor, perhaps, a viewer. So that's our Inum set up. And then the next step we need to do is
to actually use it is to assign a virtual user to this particular role. So we can do let's say
user role. And this is of type a role. So that is a type of our Inum here. And then we can just
simply assign the appropriate role by doing role dot. And then we have a dropdown that tells us
our role. So we can say role equals admin, for example. So this role admin is just an alias
all the number zero. So this one here, if I hover over it, has a value of zero, and then it's
automatically the sequential. So the next one is one, and then the next one is two. So you can see
the TypeScript assigns the values by default starting from zero. You can also assign custom values.
So either numbers or strings. So if you're not happy with zero, one and two, for example,
what you could do is you can start off and say, I want to start off at maybe 200. So the first one
is going to be 200, and then 201, 202. But once if you want to have these as custom numbers as well,
where you could do that, if you wanted to, so you could say, for example, that is 300.
And they've got 300 of that, and it's going to continue 301. So let's say we wanted to do some
status codes. That would make some more sense. So we could say status codes, and the first one could
be success. And this has a number of 200. That's the HTTP code for that. And the next one maybe
is not found. And this is the famous 404 error, if you're into development. And then we might
have server error. And this is an error code of say 500. And now actually to find some custom
numbers. So we could say that right to find a variable and say our status code is a type status
codes. And we have a not found error or a success or whatever we want. By having this, these
status codes is going to be much better for readability purposes and debugging. And numeric
enums that we've seen here are particularly useful when working with APIs or status codes.
But we could also have ones in strings as well. So let's say instead of status codes, we want to
have an enum of direction. So this could be maybe up, it could be up like this in capitals. And
down could be zone, let's say it could be left. So now to find some custom enumeration of strings.
And then of course we just change this to direction. And then our direction is direction dots
down left or up. So one thing to be bear in mind as the behaviour for enums is that when they're
numeric, then they are bi-directional, but they're one way when using strings.
Okay, so you might be thinking Tim, that's fantastic, but what do you mean by bi-directional
and one way? Well, let's go through an example. Let's start off with a simple enum
of colour. And this is going to be a numeric one. And we have read it at one and then green
and then blue. Okay, so let's now do, for example, show you how what I mean by bi-directional.
So we could do a console log and we take the colour red.
Let's just run that and we have the value over here. Let's just bring it across of one. Okay,
now if we do another console log and say the log is of colour and so we put this in square
or square brackets, we say one, execute that. We get red. So that's bi-directional. So we can either
use actual enum value, say one red and it's going to convert it to one and we can do the opposite,
the bi-directional and actually give it the value of one and it's going to give us
the actual numeration value of red. So that's how you can convert a kind of two ways between the
integer and back again. But this is only true for a numeric value. So if you have a string,
you know, like I just showed you, another example, you can't go two ways because it's strings,
so kind of what's the point. So let's do a very simple and mini challenge. Do an enum
and try a model, a traffic light. So obviously red, yellow and green for these particular traffic lights.
Pause the video and just quickly tap that out on your TypeScript playground and then compare
what I have. So a simple traffic light might be an enum traffic light and we could just have red
set that to red. And next one would be say yellow, is yellow and
there one of course is green. They're nice and easy, we could put yellow back in capitals, couldn't we?
Keep things consistent. Okay, so we've covered enums, what about allitral types? So literal types,
let us restrict a variable to a specific set of values. Imagine it like a drop down menu,
we have say only three options. So I'm going to remove the code we have here,
and we could have an example of alignment, perhaps you're trying to align text in a paragraph,
you might have a left center, a line, right. So we could define alignment and alignments could be
a few three options, we could have left. We could also have center, so we could put a pipe symbol,
and we said center, another pipe symbol, and we can say right.
Now you can also, interestingly enough, actually do an association, so you could say right,
is effectively also center. So here we've defined an alignment variable, which only can have
three possible values, left, center, and right. So let's actually have an example of some
literal types of action. So we're going to define a different type of example, and this time it's
going to be a button size. So you can say a button size, you can say we have a type
of, and let's call it a button size, and it's going to have three possible values.
We can have small, we can have medium, all what we can have large.
And now we can actually create a button. So you can do this, kind of using normal JavaScript,
but we're going to show you how to do an actual function, which we haven't really looked at
at this current time. So it's fairly straightforward. Again, we just do function,
we define the function in a normal way that we do in JavaScript. The difference is when we
actually define the parameter, we can give it the actual type. So we have a parameter of size,
then with the code on, we say that the parameter is of type button size.
And now we can just simply just do what we want to do. So we can just pretend and say
the console log, we can say creating a size should be dollar button. And now we can just simply
execute our function. So we can say create button whoops, not on create button. And we can give
it a size. So we can say the button is going to be medium.
Let's execute that, creating a medium button. And if we try and give it a value that's not one of
these three. And if we give it a value obviously create medium large, then we get an error,
coming up saying the argwind of type medium large is not signable. This only going to allow us
would not give us an error if we actually give it a value. So let's say it's allowed. Let's
say large. If we execute that, we get creating a large button. So the lateral types are perfect
for modeling options, perhaps states or modes. And then make our code so much safer and easy to
understand. But lateral types are often used with union types to enforce strict value sets.
So let's have an example of that. So we could have for example a type of mode. And this
imagine that we have a user interface and we have a light theme or we have a dark theme. That's
hard. What's all? Sorry, we have a light mode and a dark mode. And then we want to define a theme
of modern and classic, let's see, perhaps another one of retro. So we have a theme, three options,
and we have a mode of light or dark. So this gives us a fine grain control without needing a full
enumeration. So in conclusion, both inums and literal types will pass model real-world
constraints in our code. Now inums are great for named constants, while the literal types give us
precise control over allowed values. So that's a difference. So inums are just going to give us
kind of a series of options, whereas literal types really spell out what and what we can't
actually put inside a variable. So in the next lesson, we're going to explore union
and intersection types, which is how to combine the types to build a flexible yet safe structures.